Inventory of the Garrett Family Papers 1786-1928
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Garrett Family Papers, 1786-1928.
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Mss. 69 G19
Ca. 200 items.
Papers, 1786-1928, of the Garrett family of Williamsburg, Virginia.
Garrett Family,; Dr. Robert M. Garrett,; Alexander C. Garrett,; B. F. Garrett,; Lottie. Garrett,; David E. Cronin.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
Gift: Ca. 200 items, March 1969.
Biographical/Historical Information
This collection contains material that starts with the marriage of Dr. Robert Major Garrett (1807-1885), to Susan Comfort Winder (1812-1878) and expands to include their families and their children.
Paternal Genealogy
Richard Garrett (d. 1825), married Ann Major (1785-1855), and had several children including but may not be limited to the following: Richard R. Garrett (b. 1801); Dr. Robert Major Garrett (1807-1885); Polly Garrett, William Garrett, John Garrett and Edmund Garrett. Richard R. Garrett (b. 1801), attended William and Mary from 1828-1831. He married Laura A. and had a son George R. Garrett.
Maternal Genealogy
Thomas Gore married Comfort Quinton. They had a daughter Comfort Quinton Gore (b. 1791), who married John Hermanson Winder (b. 1784). This marriage resulted in several children including but may not be limited to the following: Susan Comfort Winder (1812-1878); Bettie A. Winder; Lauretta A. (Savage) Winder, Charlotte Winder and John E. Winder.
Dr. Robert Major Garrett (1807-1885), attended the College of William and from 1822-1826. He was a physician and later became superintendent of Eastern Lunatic Asylum of Williamsburg. He held the position of mayor of the city of Williamsburg from 1860-1861. Married to Susan Comfort Winder (1812-1878), their children include but may not be limited to the following: Benjamin F. Garrett (1821-1878); Alexander C. Garrett (b. 1823); Capt. William Robertson Garrett (1839-1904); Van Franklin Garrett (1846-1932); Mary W. Garrett (b. 1851); and Lottie Garrett. Benjamin F. Garrett (1821-1878), and Alexander C. Garrett (b. 1823), both attended the College of William and Mary. Benjamin studied law.
Capt. William Robertson Garrett (1839-1904), attended the College of William and Mary and the University of Virginia receiving a degree in law. However his law practice in Williamsburg was interrupted by the Civil War. William Robertson served as a private in the 32d Virginia regiment and was elected captain. After the war, in 1868, he married Julia Flournoy Batte and moved to Tennessee, where he was employed as a professor of mathematics and later president at Giles College, Tennessee. Thus started his varied and important career in the education field. This including becoming Giles County superintendent, 1873-1875; establishing the Peabody Normal College for teachers, 1875 and later becoming chair of American History for the University of Nashville; editing the "American Historical Magazine," 1865-1902; holding the position of state superintendent of public instruction for Tennessee, 1891-1893; and becoming president of various state and national teaching organization including the National Educational Association. He fathered eight children.
Van Franklin Garrett (1846-1932), attended the Virginia Military Institute but left early to serve in the Civil War. He then attended the College of William and Mary, the University of Virginia and the Bellevue Hospital Medical College in New York City, New York, receiving a degree in medicine. He returned to Williamsburg to farm and practice medicine. He taught at Giles College, Tennessee only to return to Williamsburg to accept a position of professorship of Natural Science at the College of William and Mary. He married Harriett Nicholls (b. 1846), and had four children: Van Franklin Garrett Jr, Carra (George Dillard) Garrett, Suzanne (Selator Montague) Garrett, and Harriet (William Hodges) Garrett.
Scope and Content Information
Correspondence of the Garrett family of Williamsburg, Va., concerning family and social news, politics, and the Civil War. Earlier letters deal mainly with business and political news, as several Garrett family members, including Richard R. Garrett, Alexander C. Garrett, and Dr. Robert M. Garrett, were involved in the politics of 19th century Virginia. Correspondence of Dr. Robert M. Garrett and his brothers Alexander C. Garrett and B. F. Garrett concerning the sale of "Yardley," Northampton County, Va. There are letters written to Dr. Robert M. Garrett's daughter, Lottie Garrett, by David E. Cronin concerning his memoir of the Vest Mansion and the Civil War occupation of Williamsburg and portraits owned by Lottie Garrett.
Includes letters, dated from 1897 to 1911, written to Miss Lottie Garrett by American novelist Mary Johnston (1870-1936). Also includes a letter, 25 December 1863, written by Asa Hartz, a Confederate soldier held at Johnson's Island Federal Prison, describing the everyday life of a prisoner during the Civil War. Collection contains certificate, 1832, of services of a black Revolutionary War soldier.
Arrangement
Organization
This collection is organized into six series:
1. Letters
2. Accounts
3. Legal Documents
4. Writtings
5. Calling and Place Cards
6. Printed Matter
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically by date with those items lacking a date located at the end of each series. Series 1 is divided into subseries by ten or twenty year increments depending on the amount of letters.
Additional Related Material
Related Material
Materials related to this collection is the account book, 1842-1849, of B. F. Garrett, attorney, Williamsburg, Va. It includes accounts with John Tyler, Jr.
B. F. Garrett Account Book, Manuscripts and Rare Books Department, Swem Library, College of William and Mary. B. F. Garrett Account Book, 1842-1849.158 p. bound volume 32 cm.Collection number: Mss. MsV Al6
Index Terms
Family Names:
Garrett Family.
Persons:
Garrett, Robert M., Dr.; Garrett, Alexander C.; Garrett, B. F.; Garrett, Lottie.; Cronin, David E., b. 1839.
Subjects:
Williamsburg (Va.)--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783--African Americans.
Geographical Names:
Yardley (Northampton County, Va.)
Components List
  Series 1: Letters
- Letters, 1825-1928, n.d. (Box 1-2)
  - Letters, 1825-1839., 7 items. (Box-folder 1:1)
    - John S. Meehan, Washington, to Robert Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 21 Feb[ruary] 1825., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Excuses himself for not writing sooner as he was ill; believed that Mr. Armstrong gave him [RG] the receipt for the eight dollars for the entire liquidation of his account; informs him that his father's account is now entirely settled; regrets that he [RG] finds it "inconvenient, at present, to patronize the Star."
    - [?], W[illia]msburg, [Virginia], to "Sir" [?], n.p., 16 March 1830., 2 pages. ALS. Torn. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Defines happiness as consisting "of the exercises of the mind, and the development of its various faculties"; believes learning is for the "favoured many"; advocates the stimulation of the mind as a way to bring moral virtues into the light "from the darkness in which they were enveloped, and the latent sparks of the moral faculty, Concience [sic], & virtue [are] kindled into a flame and excited to action."
    - S. Godwin, Washington, [D.C.], to Alexander C. Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 10 Sept[ember] 1832., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Congratulates him on being elected Attorney for the counties of James City and Warwick[?]; asks if he has turned Scott or Seward Whig since those counties are Whig; finds it suspicious especially when he [ACG] speaks of carrying the Locofocos by 8,000; will examine Mr. Mason's father's papers if he [SG] is called an heir or a son of Adam Mason; asks him to tell Bowden that the Groves land claim will be reopened and a new investigation begun; will call the claim up for consideration with Mr. Barbour and expects to get it.
    - Madison, n.p., to Susan Winder, Eastern Shire, near Eastville, Northampton Co[unty], Virginia, 10 Oct[ober 1835?]., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Shares details of his journey from Norfolk by ship; was welcomed quite kindly by the Garretts; mentions family and mutual friends; informs her that "they will never forgive you if you do not come when Rosina comes"; will board at Mr. Bicks', as will Rosina.
    - W[illia]m P. Nottingham, Mount Brilliant, to Dr. Robert M. Garrett, W[illia]msburg, Virginia, 4 May 1838., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Was approached by Mr. N.I. Winder as to the least amount that would purchase the one half of Yardley that belongs to Nottingham, Garrett, and Lauretta; found the way Mr. Winder wanted to advertise the sale objectionable; has raised the purchase price to $11,000-12,000, subject to his and Lauretta's approval; informs him that there are many people wanting to buy Yardley, and that Peter S. Bowdoin has offered more than a fair price for it; hopes to sell the whole of Yardley for $10,500 at private sale.
    - W[illia]m P. Nottingham, Northampton C[oun]ty, Virginia, to Dr. Rob[er]t M. Garrett, W[illia]msburg, Virginia, 5 Dec[ember] 1838., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Believes that Yardley will sell for $9,000 in August at public sale; is eager to sell the house, as is Lauretta, as it seems to be depreciating; informs him that this year's rent will be paid in grain; mentions that Lauretta and Charlotte are in agreement as to the sale of the plantation next to Yardley; informs him of the death of W[illia]m P. Custis, who has given his entire estate, worth $80,000 to $100,000 to his widow.
    - Nath[anie]l I. Winder, Eastville, [Virginia], to Doctor Robert M. Garrett, Williamsburg, [Virginia], 27 April 1839., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:1)
      Was convinced that the August Court day would be a better time to sell Yardley; added into the advertisement for the sale statements concerning average crop yield; believes that Yardley will sell for more at private sale, rather than public sale; informs him that Mr. Nottingham concurs and is willing to sell Yardley for $9,500 or even $9,000; suggests not selling for less than $9,500 at this time; will send again the $87.91 he owes him if he [RMG] will send a receipt.
  - Letters, 1840-1849., 17 items. (Box-folder 1:2-3)
    - Rose Winder, Pembroke, to Mrs. Anne Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 6 May 184?., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Explains that she did not intend to be negligent in not writing; remembers the time she spent in Williamsburg with fondness; informs her that her mother had recovered rapidly after she [RW] returned from Williamsburg, but had been attacked by a disease of the eyes a fortnight ago; feels that the county is "unusually tame" as no visitors have arrived yet; shares news of friends and family and sends her love.
    - Rose [Winder], Williamsburg, [Virginia], to Miss Anne Parker, Eastville, Virginia, 19 Dec[ember] 1840., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Has been ill with a sore throat and was unable to write; describes herself as "too fat, & too happy, to go to the E[astern] Shore sooner than 4th July"; gives news of many mutual acquaintances.
    - Rose [Winder], Williamsburg, [Virginia], to Miss Anne Parker, Eastville, Virginia, 11 Feb[ruary 18]41., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Thanks her for her well-wishes; fears being a "nominal christian" and has fallen in love with the "christian character"; believes there was not a better man than the pastor of her church and fears the "lukewarmness of his flock... will shorten his days, the recent dissipation seems to give him so much pain"; did not go to the vice-president's, John Tyler's, party the night before because she was tired and sleepy and the weather was damp; gives news of all the people currently in town; misses her home but knows Mrs. G[arrett] would like her to stay till after the fourth of July.
    - Jno. [John] W.H. Parker, Drummond Town, to Benjamin F. Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 24 Ap[ri]l [18]42., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Has just returned from a trip to Northampton County, accompanied by his cousin Miss Wise; saw many young ladies in Northampton that he [BFG] is not acquainted with, mentioning Miss Neale, Miss Wilson, Miss Ellen Upshur, Miss S. Parker, Miss Mary Tazewell, and Miss Skipwith; mentions that having an "excellent heart... is the estimable quality in a young lady"; is "anxious to see the Alumni Association put into full and complete operation" and believes that "a glorious institution may be established" regarding the association; informs him that his friend Jno. G. Upshur is "as true a friend of Wm. & Mary as can be found anywhere. He vindicated her character and claims to the patronage of the south in a handsomely written and spirited argument in the Richmond Enquirer last year after his visit"; is looking forward to seeing everyone on the fourth of July.
    - Rose Winder, Pembroke, to Alex[ander] C. Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 4 June 1842., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Has been participating in a whirl of social events which she has enjoyed, but later questioned whether that were all there is to life; has been taught "to enjoy with liveliest zest the pure outpourings of disinterested friendship, & the exalted sentiments of the upright, cultivated mind"; has made some new acquaintances and would set him up with one, except that she is eighteen months older than he; informs him that Ma and Pa are expecting him this summer; was glad to hear "the cause of temperance was prospering so in Wmsbg" and mentions that "some of my favourites have signed the pledge."
    - Geo[rge] H. Cabaniss, Petersburg, [Virginia], to Benjamin F. Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 7 July 1842., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Is upset to think that distance has caused their friendship to falter; mentions that "once more the Star of my Destiny beamed on the horizon of my brightest dreams" by the appearance of Fanny, with whom he is in love; believes he will be surprised to learn that "Bat" [?] is engaged to a wealthy and accomplished girl; will help him in any way he can if he wishes to relocate to Mr. Jones's neighborhood, and believes that his chances of success with a girl of Mr. Jones's home are quite favorable; informs him that their fourth of July was quite dull and less liquor drunk than anyone would have guessed; is a devotee to the cause of temperance, and remarks that it seems to be predominate.
    - S.J. Bowden, Richmond, [Virginia], to R.R. Garrett, Yorktown, Virginia, 8 March 1843., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Informs him that they are now debating the convention question and assures him that the bill will be defeated; hopes to be home by the 20th as they are trying to adjourn by that time; has much interesting news to share with him about "the Whig and Democratic Conventions and other incidents of the season"; informs him that "The Assembly has helped the bill relative to the Bruton Parish fund, according to the wish of York, and she is now entitled to demand and recieve [sic] her own, and to dispose of it as she may please."
    - W[illiam] F. Weeks, Berryville, to B[enjamin] F. Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 12 Nov[ember] 1843., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:2)
      Has had little time to write as what time he had "has been devoted to some fair lassies... a courting man should never be held accountable for delay of this kind"; enjoyed the time he and Conway had at Old Point; was prevented by rain in "executing my designs upon Miss ---"; has been convinced to go to the South this winter, which will prevent his return to college; encloses $10 in thanks to him; asks for all the news from college.
    - J.C. Sheldon, Williamsburg, [Virginia], to R.R. Garrett, near Yorktown, Virginia, 13 April 1844., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Informs him that his friends in New York are seeking some oysters, asks about the "prospect of their gratification."
    - R[ichard] Eppes, City Point, Virginia, to Alexander Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 24 June 1844., 1 page. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Will explain the neglect of his not writing when he comes to Williamsburg on the third; expects that he will come to stay with him at least a month; details the diversions in store for him, such as "an introduction to the belles of Petersburg & the neighboring counties, a trip to Nottoway, a visit to some of my pretty cousins in Greensville, and frequent discussions on politics"; informs him of his [RE] mother's death; asks to be remembered to their mutual friends.
    - Alex[ander Garrett], Smithfield, [Virginia], to "brother" B[enjamin] F. Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 12 October 1844., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Explains that he forgot his diploma and his certificate in Williamsburg and gives him directions on how to procure each and where to send them so that he will have them before the Isle of Wight County court begins; explains that they were required of Ruffin before they would allow him to qualify; describes some people he has met in Smithfield already; is not sure of his prospects there as yet.
    - Richard R. Garrett, Senate Chamber, Richmond, [Virginia] to "wife" Laura A. Garrett, Yorktown, York County, Virginia, 27 Jan[uar]y 1845., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Describes his trip to Richmond; informs her that "we had the most exciting session by far we have had this winter. The democrats made the whigs back out fairly from the election of a U.S. Senator"; describes a party he attended for Miss Hill and Mrs. Ashton at Mr. Parishe's; was ill from the food at the party but is now recovered; informs her that he saw no one at the party "as handsome & to my eyes as sweet as my own Laura"; called on Martha but found her indisposed and does not believe she will ever be in good health; has heard that Louisiana Barryham[?] has the ague and fever; mentions a revival in progress at the Fourth Baptist Church and that he went to hear Brother Walker at the Second Church; implores her to write to him.
    - William S. Christian, Northampton, Virginia, to "friend" Benjamin F. Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 30 April 1845., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Writes to inform him that he is to be married on the 25th of June to a "splendid woman in every attribute"; has been very busy going to three to four parties a week; invites other members of the Garrett family through this letter; implores him to come to wait on him at the wedding.
    - Ja[me]s W. Spratley, Smithfield, Virginia, to Alexander C. Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 14 June 1846., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Has neglected to write as he has been very busy with his tax accounts; informs him that there is nothing happening in Smithfield and "so you must content yourself this time by simply hearing of my dreadful melancholy and despairing thoughts"; mentions the rumors that he is courting Mag again as having started at the wedding in Surry and denies any truth to them; describes the lady's anger at him as being so great the "I do not even visit Mag nor even walk the street with her in her evening strolls"; missed seeing him at J. Wilson's wedding; mentions the depression that he felt while at the wedding in remembering the time he'd spent there the year before and how he fully expected "a favourable result" to his courting; received an invitation to act as a groomsman at John Corsen's wedding next week; has promised Mary and Alice Coke that he will meet them at Old Point this summer and asks if he will go with them also.
    - B[enjamin] F. Garrett, Halifax Co[urt] House, to "brother" Dr. Ro[bert] M. Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 7 July 1846., 4 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Asks him to write when he can; describes the "grand celebration here on the 4th" where he gave the address on the subject on Texas, Oregon, and the Mexican War; received many compliments on his address; has decided to speak on every occasion due to the successes he's had in addressing the Court and the crowd on the 4th; mentions that business is slow and has only four suits this term; is anxious for success; has not called on any ladies but will write to Susan if he does begin to court; will meet Mr. Leigh at Charlotte Court; has misplaced his account but is sure Mr. Leigh will pay the amount owed; believes Mr. Leigh owes him $30 but asks if he could send the account with his next letter.
    - Charlotte [?], n.p., to "sister" Lauretta A. Winder, W[illia]msburg, Virginia, 16 Dec[ember] 1847., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Has not written before this because she has been very busy since she [LAW] left; shares news of many acquaintances and their goings-on, including weddings and courtships.
    - W[illia]m P. Nottingham, H[ickory] Grounds, N[orthampton] County, to Lauretta A. Winder, W[illia]msburg, Virginia, 31 Aug[ust] 1848., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:3)
      Received the articles and letter she sent by Mr. Wheeler and sends her many thanks for them; has sent her a box by Mr. Wheeler containing peaches, dried pears, and honey; has paid off her account with [?] N's store; informs her of several deaths, including that of W[illia]m Bayly from an illness resulting from hemorrhage of the lungs, Mr. Marshall from worn-out constitution, and Dr. Yerby's youngest child from consumption; believes Mrs. Leah Bowden will not live much longer as her health is declining rapidly; mentions that Rose's cousins, Mrs. and Dr. Hayes and two daughters, will come to visit her after their visit to the President as Mrs. Hayes is the sister of President Polk; is pleased to tell her that Charlotte's health is improving and will soon be well again.
  - Letters, 1850-1859., 26 items. (Box-folder 1:4-6)
    - Th[omas] H. Bayly, Washington, to Jno. [John] H. Pumphrey, n.p., 27 Jan[uary 18]50., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Describes the efforts he has made on his [JHP] behalf in writing to various people; informs him that no apology is necessary as he was glad to serve his constituent and friend.
    - A[lexander] C. Garrett, Philadelphia, [Penn.], to "brother" Dr. Ro[bert] M. Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 31 May 1850., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Escorted Mrs. Orgain to City Point on his way to Philadelphia; asks that he tell Miss Lauretta that he delivered her package to Mr. Ryle in Baltimore safely; felt "very queer in being surrounded by my black fellow citizens, and in seeing the deference and respect shown them. They are the priviledged [sic] class -- the aristocracy of the Quaker City... my wrath has cooled, and I endeavor not to notice these sable gentlemen"; describes a case he is currently working on with Mr. Boone; have made the acquaintance of an Englishman who wishes him to accompany him to Canada and then on to England, but he cannot for the money; has also met a Virginian who wishes him to accompany him to York.
    - Th[omas] H. Bayly, Washington, to A[lexander] C. Garrett, Williamsburg, Virginia, 22 Aug[ust 18]50., 2 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)
      Gave his letter to Judge Underwood, who has only had the time recently to reply; encloses Underwood's letter to him; informs him that the outcome of the slavery bill is very uncertain as yet; mentions that if the Texas Bill is taken up in advance of the Territorial Bills, the slavery bill will be defeated.
      This letter was included within the letter listed below; J.R. Underwood, n.p., to [Thomas H.] Bailey [sic], n.p., n.d.
    - J.R. Underwood, n.p., to [Thomas H.] Bailey [sic], n.p., n.d., 3 pages. ALS. (Box-folder 1:4)